If you ask most people what the best universities in the UK are, they will probably answer Oxford or Cambridge.
如果你问大多数人英国最好的大学是哪所，他们很可能会回答牛津或剑桥。
These elite educational establishments were founded 800 years ago; since then being offered a place has been seen as the pinnacle of academic life.
这两所顶尖的教育机构始建于800年前，从那以后，能被录取就被视为学术生涯的巅峰成就。
Despite these being the places to go to for high-achieving students, the number of undergraduate students from the UK attending Oxbridge (Oxford and Cambridge) has dropped.
尽管这两所大学是优等生们梦寐以求的求学之地，但就读于牛剑（牛津和剑桥的合称）的英国本土本科生数量却有所下降。
Student figures from the Higher Education Statistics Agency and from the universities show 7% fewer UK undergraduates at Oxford and 5% fewer at Cambridge compared with 2007-08.
高等教育统计局和两所大学的学生数据显示，与2007-2008学年相比，牛津大学的英国本科生减少了7%，剑桥大学则减少了5%。
Of course competition for places is intense, and British students compete with those from abroad.
当然，入学竞争十分激烈，英国本土学生需要和海外学生同台角逐。
Overseas undergraduate student numbers rose by 51% at Oxford and 65% at Cambridge.
牛津大学的海外本科生数量增长了51%，剑桥大学则增长了65%。
Oxford says it recruits the "best talent from around the world"; and on postgraduate courses at Cambridge, there are now more overseas students than those from the UK.
牛津大学称其致力于招收“全球最优秀的人才”，而在剑桥大学的研究生课程中，海外学生的数量如今已经超过了英国本土学生。
The BBC's education correspondent Sean Coughlan explains that in the UK "there have been calls for more places for disadvantaged youngsters as well as ethnic minority students and white working-class youngsters."
英国广播公司教育记者肖恩·考夫兰表示，在英国，“一直有呼声要求为弱势群体青少年、少数族裔学生以及白人工薪阶层青少年提供更多入学名额”。
But despite an ambition to improve social mobility, the total number of UK students being awarded places at Oxbridge has gone down.
但尽管两所大学都有提升社会流动性的愿景，获得牛剑录取资格的英国本土学生总数还是出现了下滑。
Sir Peter Lampl, chairman of the Sutton Trust social mobility charity, told the BBC that "Oxford and Cambridge attract many international students, but they must ensure that their student body is balanced…
萨顿信托基金会（一家致力于促进社会流动性的慈善机构）主席彼得·兰普尔爵士向英国广播公司表示：“牛津和剑桥吸引了众多国际学生，但它们必须确保学生群体的构成保持平衡……
This means letting in UK and international students based on ability and not on ability to pay."
这意味着录取英国本土学生和国际学生时，应基于能力而非经济支付能力。”
But an Oxford spokeswoman said "Sustaining excellence requires diversity, and our commitment to achieving this balance, and making Oxford more reflective of modern society includes reaching out to and selecting the best talent from all over the world."
但牛津大学的一位女发言人回应称：“保持卓越离不开多样性，我们致力于实现这种平衡，让牛津大学更能反映现代社会的面貌，这其中就包括发掘并录取全球各地最优秀的人才。”
With overseas students from outside the EU paying higher fees for tuition, is the decline in places for British students inevitable?
由于欧盟以外的海外学生需要支付更高的学费，英国本土学生的入学名额减少是否是必然趋势？
This is not known, but other prestigious British universities such as UCL and Exeter have seen numbers of UK student rise.
目前尚无定论。但其他英国顶尖高校，如伦敦大学学院和埃克塞特大学，其英国本土学生的数量却有所上升。
One solution may be to expand and offer more places.
一种解决办法或许是扩大招生规模，提供更多入学名额。
But whatever happens, competition for an Oxbridge place will always remain high.
但无论如何，想要考上牛剑，竞争的激烈程度永远不会降低。